在这个视频中
in this video
我们来看看
we're going to take a look at
FILE结构体和标准IO流函数
file structs and the standard io streaming functions
到目前为止
so up until this point
当我们想要与文件交互时
when we've wanted to interact with a file
使用的都是系统调用read和write
we've used the raw syscalls read and write
read和write
now read and write
操作的都是文件描述符
operate on something that's known as a file descriptor
通常
and typically
文件描述符是通过open系统调用获得的
a file descriptor is obtained through the use of the open syscall
比如像这样open /home/hacker/class_notes.txt
so we may do something like open /home/hacker/class_notes.txt
这会返回一个文件描述符
and that's going to return a file descriptor
看看我们的示例代码
now looking at our code example here
可以看到文件描述符是一个整数
we see that the file descriptor is an integer
实际上我们可以printf输出它的值
in fact we can even call printf on that integer to figure out what the value is
大多数时候，在你的代码中
most of the time in your own code
打开的第一个文件
the first file that you open
会返回文件描述符3
is going to return the file descriptor 3
这意味着什么
so what is the significance of this
而且为什么我要把这个3传回给内核
and why do I need to pass this 3 back to the kernel
在我要用这个文件的时候
when I want to interact with this file
在内核内部
well inside the kernel
每个进程都有一个进程文件表
for every process there is a process file table
这个进程文件表一边是一个整数列表
and this process file table is a listing of these integer values
每一个整数值
and for every one of these integer values
对应着一个指向file结构体的指针
there is a pointer to a file struct
这个file结构放在另一个的表中
and this file struct exists in a separate table
叫全局文件表
known as the global file table
全局文件表
now the Global File table
对系统上打开的每个文件都有一个条目
has an entry for every file that is currently open on the system
全局文件表中的file结构体
and the file struct inside the Global File table
是文件在内核中的表示形式
is kind of the kernels representation of the file
所以它记录了
so it's going to have information
像文件路径
like the path
以及在文件中的偏移量
as well as the offset into the file
这个文件中的偏移量是什么
now what is the offset
好，若一个进程read一次后，再次read该文件
well what happens if a process calls read on a file and then calls read again
我们希望第二次read
we would expect the second read
能从第一次读到的位置继续
to continue from where the first one ended
这个文件内偏移量记录着
the offset keeps track of where into the file
当前访问到了文件中的哪个位置
are we currently accessing
file结构体中还有一个字段
now one of the additional fields that's in a file struct
inode指针
is the inode pointer
inode指针指向一个inode结构体
now the inode pointer points to an inode struct
如果你上过文件系统取证的课
if you've taken a File Systems for forensics class
你可能对inode进行了更深入的研究
you may have explored the inode in a bit greater depth
我们可以简单地认为
we're just going to say
inode表示一些底层信息
that the inode represents some of the lower level information
关于文件以及如何在硬件层面访问它
about the file and how it is accessed on hardware
它会有类似扇区、块之类的信息
so it's going to have information like kind of the sector block
还有字节偏移量
and then byte offset
表示数据物理上存储在哪里
where the physical bytes are located on the back media
所以每次我们调用read
so every time that we call read
我们都会做上下文切换，切换到内核
we are going to do a context switch into the kernel
然后内核必须
the kernel then has to perform this translation
将文件描述符，转换成file结构体
from the file descriptor to the file struct
找到inode
to the inode
从物理介质中拿数据
to then grab the bytes off of the physical media
再切换上下文，回到用户空间
to then context switch back to userland
然后我们就可以
where we can then
处理我们从文件中获取的字节
work with the bytes that we're trying to access from the file
这不是一个小工作量
this is a non trivial amount of work
而且每次调用read或write都会经历
and this occurs every time that we call read or write
我们能做得更好吗?
can we do better
libc有性能更高的一类函数
so libc has a class of functions that can be more performant
这些标准IO流函数
these standard io streaming functions
包括fopen fread和fwrite
include fopen fread and fwrite
还有更多
and there's many more
这两者之间有何不同
and now what's different about them
首先我们看看fopen
well first if we look at fopen
它不返回文件描述符
it doesn't return a file descriptor
它返回一个文件指针
it returns a file pointer
fread和fwrite
similarly fread and fwrite
的参数也不再是文件描述符了
also don't work on file descriptors
它们依靠这些文件指针
they're working on these file pointers
我们来看看他们的表现
so lets take a look at their performance
然后我们会讨论它们是如何工作的
and then we'll talk about how they work
好的
okay so
这里有一个C程序叫做read_loop.c
up here I have a C program called read_loop.c
在main中
inside of main
我们有一个大小为0x1000字节的缓冲区
we have a buffer of size hex 1000 bytes
然后我们open /dev/urandom
we're then going to call open on /dev/urandom
所以我们会读入随机字节
so we're going to be reading in random bytes
在for循环中
inside of a for loop
我们调用read
we call read
我们每批次读取0x20字节
and we are reading in batches of hex 20 bytes
我们会读入0x20字节的随机值
we're going to read in hex 20 random bytes
我们总共要做5万次
and we're going to do this 50 thousand times
我们编译read_loop.c
so let's compile read_loop.c
看看运行它需要多长时间
and let's see how long that takes to run
能看到大约是0.014 - 0.015秒
we see here it's about 0.014 0.015 seconds
好的
okay
我还有第二个C程序fread_loop.c
now I have a second C program called fread_loop.c
非常相似
which is very similar
有0x1000字节的缓冲区
we have a buffer of hex 1000 bytes
我们将用fopen打开/dev/urandom
we're going to call fopen on /dev/urandom
在for循环中，我们将调用fread
inside of our for loop we're going to call fread
每次读入0x20字节
and we're going to fread hex 20 bytes
同样，我们将循环5万次
and again we're going to do this for 50 000 iterations inside of our for loop
那么我们编译fread_loop.c
so let's compile fread_loop.c
看看这需要多长时间
let's see how long this takes to run
好吧
okay
我们看到0.004 0.005
so we see 0.004 0.005
运行时间大概是之前的三分之一
so roughly it's about a third of the the run time
我想先展示一件事
now there's one more thing that I'd like to kind of show
在下面几张幻灯片中，我们会深入研究其中的原因
and we'll delve into why in the next couple slides
但现在值得一看
but it's worth looking at right now
我要做的是
what I'm going to do is
strace这两个程序
I'm going to strace each program
我们把错误输出重定向到标准输出
we're going to redirect standard error to standard out
方便我们grep它
so that I can grep it
我感兴趣的东西是
and what I'm interested in
每个程序调用read系统调用的次数
is how many times does each program call the syscall read
左边这个是我们的read_loop
so the one on the left here which was our read_loop
调用了5万次read
calls read 50 thousand times all about
这没问题
and that makes sense
因为我们在一个循环中调用了5万次read
because we're calling read 50 thousand times in a loop
在这里
well this one here
我们在for循环中调用50,000次read
we're calling read inside a for loop of 50,000
可以预计会调用50,000次read
so we'd expect about 50,000 read calls
现在在第二个程序中，fread_loop
now in the second program fread_loop
我们做同样的事情
let's do that same thing
我们strace fread_loop
we're going to strace fread_loop
把错误输出重定向到标准输出
we'll redirect standard error to standard in
这样我们就可以grep它了
so that we can grep it
我们感兴趣的是read开头的行
and I'm interested in the lines that begin with read
找到了392个这样的行
and we see that we have 392 instances
数量大大减少了
and that's significantly less
每次我们调用read
remember every time that we call read
都会进行从用户空间到内核的上下文切换
we are doing that context switch from user space to the kernel
然后我们在这些表之间进行转换
then we're doing that translation across those tables
然后访问硬盘拿到数据
to then go touch the hardware to get the bytes
然后切换会用户空间
and then translate or context switch back to user land
当我们调用read时，这做了5万次
and we're doing that 50 thousand times when we call read
但用fread时
but use an fread
我们只做了392次
we're only doing that 392 times
这就是运行时间差异的原因
and that is the reason for this run time difference
我们来看看为什么会这样
so let's take a look at why exactly that is
这些函数作用于 FILE结构体
so these functions work on file structs
而不是文件描述符
instead of file descriptors
FILE结构体包含一堆指针
and the file struct contains a bunch of pointers
用来缓冲用户的读写请求
that are used to buffer the reading and writing that's requested by user
因为我们减少了实际发生的原始读写次数
and because we reduce the number of raw reads and writes that actually occur
减少了上下文切换
there's less context switching
就提升了性能
which results in increased performance
我刚说了FILE结构体有一堆用于缓冲的指针
now I said that the file struct contains a bunch of pointers that are used for buffering
这些是我们将在本节课讨论的
here's some of them that we're going to talk about in this lecture
如果你对FILE结构体的完整样子感兴趣
if you are interested in the file struct as a whole
我强烈建议你看看这张幻灯片底部的链接
I would highly suggest that you check out the link at the bottom of this slide
里面有FILE结构体完整定义的源码
which contains the source with the io file struct definition
但说到缓冲
but to talk about buffering
我们只关注这些值
we're just going to focus on these values here
第一个是flags值
the first is the flags value
flags的几个高有效位是定值
now the higher order bits of the flags value is a magic value
剩下的部分用来做标志
and the rest of it is used for flags
这些标志表明
now these flags indicate
例如，打开文件是为了读还是写
for instance whether or not the file is open for reading or writing
我记得代码中定义的是
I believe in the source the actual definition used is
不读，不写
no read and no write
所以如果想写，要设置不读
so if I wanted to write I would set no read
如果想读，设置不写
if I wanted to read I would set no write
但重点是
but the point is
flags值决定如何设置缓冲
the flags value determines how the buffering is going to be set up
以及我们该怎样理解它是如何与文件交互的
and how we need to think about how we're going to interact with this file conceptually
下面有8个指针
next we have 8 pointers
前三个与读有关
the first three are related to reading
有一个ptr、一个end和一个base
there's a ptr an end and a base
然后有三个和写有关
then there are three related for writing
也有一个ptr、一个end和一个base
where there's again a ptr an end and a base
最后有2个指针
and then we have two
它们与整个缓冲区有关
that are related to the buffer as a whole
分别是base和end
which has a base and an end
这里的顺序
now the order here
有点奇怪
is a little weird
但这是它在源文件中的定义
but this is how it's defined in the source
可以这样想
the way to think about it
base是这片区域的开头
is the base is the beginning of a region
end是结尾
the end is the end of a region
ptr是当前的处理到的
then the ptr is kind of the current location that we're working with
在下面几张幻灯片，我们会看到这些指针移来移去
now we'll see these pointers kind of move around in the next couple slides
以理解它们是如何使用的
to get an idea of how they're used
当调用fread时
so when fread is called
你可能会认为，你在从一个文件中读取数据
you would think that you're going to be reading from a file
文件系统上的文件
like a file on the file system
但事实并非如此
but that's not actually what occurs
在你调用fread时
when you call fread
这个函数会立马尝试
the function is going to immediately
与内存中的缓冲区进行交互
try and interact with this buffer in memory
这里应该保存了目标文件的数据
that should be holding bytes of the file
这个缓冲区
and this buffer gets loaded
会在需要时载入文件数据
when it when needed with the bytes of the file
所以一开始
so initially
在我们以读的方式打开文件时
when we open the file for reading
会在堆上分配一个缓冲区
a buffer should be allocated on the heap
应该是一个内存页大小
and it should be about a page in size
大概是0x1000字节
so it's going to be about hex 1000 bytes
缓冲区的开头由buf_base定义
the beginning of this buffer is defined by buf_base
缓冲区的结尾由buf_end定义
and the end of this buffer is defined by buf_end
因为我们是读取数据
and since we're going to be reading
这个缓冲区完全用于读
this buffer is used entirely for reading
所以缓冲区的开头也是read_base
so the beginning of the buffer is read_base
缓冲区的末尾也是read_end
and the end of the buffer is read_end
到目前为止一切正常
so far so good
现在我们读取了0字节
now we've actually read 0 bytes so far
我们只是载入了文件开头一页的数据到缓冲区
we've just filled the buffer with the beginning of the file
这就是为什么我们的读指针
and that's why our read pointer
它可以理解成我们当前在文件中的位置
which kind of represents where are we currently in the file
还在缓冲区的开头
is at the beginning of the buffer
当我们调用fread
now once we call fread
我们消耗了一些缓冲区中的数据
we've consumed some of these bytes from the buffer
此时，read_ptr向前移动到我们读完的位置
when that occurs the read pointer advances past all of the bytes that we've read
所以fread会返回
and so what's returned from fread
read_base和read_ptr之间的所有内容
is everything between read_base and read pointer
这些是已经读了的数据
and so those are the bytes that have already been read
下一次调用fread时
now the next time read is called
会返回read_ptr指向的位置
it'll begin returning bytes from where read pointer is
依次类推
and this will continue
直到我们读完这个缓冲区
until we've read everything that is in this buffer
这时候
and at that point
read_ptr指向缓冲区的末尾
read pointer has reached the end of the buffer
到达了read_end
and it has also reached read end
表示我们消耗完了读缓冲区中的数据
and so now we've consumed all of the bytes that are in the read buffer
此时，我们需要刷新读缓冲区
at this point we need to refresh the read buffer
我们通过执行read系统调用来实现它
and we do that by performing the syscall read
这就是幕后发生的事情
this is what happens under the hood
在你调用fread时，这对你是不可见的
it's invisible to you when you're calling fread
但在幕后
but under the hood
该函数将调用系统调用read
the function is going to call the syscall read
用下一个0x1000未读字节，重填这个缓冲区
and refill this buffer with on the next hex 1000 unread bytes
然后会重置read_ptr指向read_base
and then it will reset the read pointer back to read base
这样我们就可以重复这个过程
so that we can repeat this process
所以每读0x1000字节，才调用read系统调用
so we're only calling the syscall read every hex 1000 bytes
这在我们每次只读取少量数据时，非常有效
which is significantly more efficient if we're doing smaller reads
在某个时刻
now at some point
我们将到达文件的末尾
we're going to reach the end of the file
所以我们从文件中读取的
and so we may read from the file
不能填满缓冲区
but not fill the buffer
此时
and when we reach that point
所发生的是，我们读入数据
what happens is we read in the bytes
将read_end指向文件数据在缓冲区中的结束位置
and we set read_end to be the location in the buffer where the file ends
read_ptr依然指向read_base
and read pointer is still back at read base
因为我们刚将文件的最后一块加载到缓冲区中
because we just loaded the last chunk of the file into the buffer here
这样read_ptr指向到read_end时
so then read pointer could advance until read_end
就是文件的结尾
and that would be the end of the file
对于写入，我们会调用fwrite
now for writing we're going to call fwrite
调用write时
when you call write
通常是写入到一个文件
normally it goes write to a file
但当我们调用fwrite时
but if we call fwrite
它不会直接到文件中
it's not going to go directly to the file
我们实际上是在和中间的缓冲内存进行交互
there's this intermediary buffery memory that we're actually interacting with
所以我们可以这样想
and so when we think about it
fwrite会直接写入缓冲区，而不是文件
fwrite is going to write to a buffer not to a file
我们看看它是如何工作的
let's see how that works
非常类似fread
very similarly
buf_base是这个缓冲区的开头
buf_base is the beginning of this buffer
buf_end是缓冲区的末尾
buf_end is the end of the buffer
它大概有一内存页那么大
again it's about a page in size
0x1000字节
so hex 1000 bytes
write_base是缓冲区的开始
write base is the beginning of the buffer
write_end是缓冲区的末尾
write end is the end of the buffer
write_ptr记录着下一个字节写入的位置
write pointer tracks where should the next bytes be written
因为我们还没有写任何东西
since we haven't written anything yet
所以write_ptr指向缓冲区开头
write pointer points to the beginning of the buffer
一旦我们调用了一次fwrite
now once we have called fwrite once
会有一些字节被写入缓冲区
there'll be some bytes that get written into the buffer
write_ptr会前进
and the write pointer advances to mark
标记出写入字节的末尾在哪里
where is the end of the bytes that we have written
下次调用fwrite时
now the next time that fwrite is called
数据会直接写入到write_ptr指向的地址
those bytes will be written to the address to find by the write pointer
所以我们在做的是
and so what we're doing
用想要写入文件的数据，填充这个缓冲区
is we are slowly filling up this buffer with the bytes that we intend to write to the file
不过，他们还没有填满缓冲区
they haven't gotten there yet though
这些数据就放在缓冲区中
right now they're just sitting in this buffer
当我们填满了缓冲区
now once we filled the buffer
write_ptr到达write_end
and the write pointer reaches write end
我们将flush(冲走)这些数据
we need to flush this out
flush是指
and by flushing it
我们会取出缓冲区的数据
we're going to take the bytes that are in the buffer
将它们提交到磁盘
and actually commit them to disk or whatever it is
或其他支撑文件存储的位置
that is backing the file
在我们flush数据时
and so when we flush
write_ptr会回到开头
the write pointer jumps back to the beginning
下次我们用fwrite写入的字节
and the next bytes that we will write from fwrite
会在缓冲区开头开始写
will start at the beginning of the buffer
这会持续下去，直到缓冲区填满并flush数据
and this process can continue until we fill the buffer and flush
或调用fflush
or the function fflush is called
这样可以手动冲走数据到文件中
so you can manually flush a file
考虑这个的时候要记住一件事
now one thing to kind of keep in mind when you are thinking about this
FILE结构体在哪里
is where is the file struct located
它实际上位于用户空间
well it's actually located in userland
这个缓冲区在哪里
where is this buffer located
缓冲区也在用户空间
well the buffer is also in userland
这些不是内核中的内存地址
these are not memory addresses that are in the kernel
我们将在下个视频中探讨其中的一些含义
and we'll explore some of the implications of that in the next video